Adam N. Goodkind

CONTACT Information Northwestern University Department of Communications

a.goodkind@u.northwestern.edu adamgoodkind.com

RESEARCH INTERESTS Combining human-computer interaction (HCI) findings with collaboration and communication (CSCW), to improve the conversational efficiency of people interacting with other people as well as with a computer (chatbot). My research uses keystroke-level analysis, information theory, and text analytics to understand cognitive processing effort and better predict the trajectory of collaboration and communication during task-oriented conversations.

EDUCATION

PhD, Northwestern University

Media, Technology & Society Program

2240 Campus Drive, Evanston, IL 60208 USA

2019–Present

PI: Darren Gergle (CollabLab)

Linguistics Department 2016–2019

PI: Klinton Bicknell (Language & Computation Lab)

Honors:

Data Science Fellowship Cognitive Science Specialist

M.A., CUNY Graduate Center

2016

Computational Linguistics

M.A. Thesis: Utilizing Linguistic Context To Improve Identification in Typed Text

Thesis Advisors: Prof. Andrew Rosenberg and Prof. Martin Chodorow

B.A., Columbia University

2007

Religion (Study of Science & Religion)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant, CollabLab, Evanston, IL, USA

2019-Present

PI: Darren Gergle

My proposed dissertation uses keystroke-level analysis to understand differences in language production and linguistic choices depending on the perceived conversational partner. By comparing a user's reaction to mistakes made by another human versus mistakes made by a computer, we can better understand how unique mental models impact collaborative work in different settings.

Research Assistant, LangComp Lab, Evanston, IL, USA

2017-2019

PI: Klinton Bicknell

Researching autism diagnoses using linguistic markers, such as semantic similarity (word vectors) and pragmatic deficiencies. Also researching how linguistic predictability affects sentence processing via eye-tracking.

Research Assistant, CUNY Speech Lab, New York, NY, USA

2012-2016

PI: Andrew Rosenberg

Research Assistant, Columbia NLP Group, New York, NY, USA

2006-2007

PI: Rebecca Passonneau

Honors and Awards Best Paper Award, Cognitive Modeling & Computational Linguistics (CMCL)

Developmental Sciences Cluster Fellowship - Finalist, Northwestern University

Data Science Fellowship, Northwestern University

USS Donald and Mary Ellen Passantino Scholarship, CUNY Graduate Center

Google Lime Connect Scholarship-Finalist

Thomas W. Smith Academic Fellowship, CUNY Graduate Center

National Science Foundation, Undergraduate Research Grant, Columbia University

2018

2018

2018

2019

2018

2019

2017

2017

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

Albert A. List Academic Fellowship King's Crown Award for Outstanding Leadership, Columbia University 2003–2007 2006

PUBLICATIONS

- 2018 Goodkind, A., Lee, M., Martin, G. E., Losh, M., & Bicknell, K. Detecting language impairments in autism: A computational analysis of semi-structured conversations with vector semantics. In *Proceedings of the Inaugural Meeting of the Society for Computation in Linguistics*. Salt Lake City, UT: Linguistic Society of America. [paper] [slides]
 - Goodkind, A. & Bicknell, K. Predictive power of word surprisal for reading times is a linear function of language model quality. In *Proceedings of the 8th Workshop on Cognitive Modeling and Computational Linguistics (CMCL 2018)*. Salt Lake City, UT: Linguistic Society of America. [paper] [slides]
- 2016 Goodkind, A., Brizan D.G. & Rosenberg, A. Utilizing Overt and Latent Linguistic Structure to Improve Keystroke-Based Authentication. Image and Vision Computing: Best of Biometrics Special Issue.
- 2015 Goodkind, A., Brizan D.G. & Rosenberg, A. Improvements to Keystroke-Based Authentication By Adding Linguistic Context. 7th IEEE Conference on Biometrics: Theory, Applications and Systems (BTAS 2015). (Slides)
 - Goodkind, A. & Rosenberg, A. Muddying The Multiword Expression Waters: How Cognitive Demand Affects Multiword Expression Production. 11th Workshop on Multiword Expressions at NAACL-HLT 2015. (Slides)
 - Brizan, D. G., **Goodkind, A.**, Koch, P., Balagani, K., Phoha, V. V., & Rosenberg, A. *Utilizing Linguistically-Enhanced Keystroke Dynamics to Predict Typist Cognition and Demographics. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, October 2015, vol. 84, 57-68.*
- 2014 Locklear, H., Govindarajan, S., Sitova, Z., **Goodkind, A.**, Brizan, D., Rosenberg, A., Phoha, V., Gasti, P., & Balagani, K. Continuous Authentication with Cognition-centric Text Production and Revision Features. Biometrics (IJCB), 2014 IEEE International Joint Conference.
- 2013 Serwadda, A., Balagani, K., Wang, Z., Koch, P., Govindarajan, S., Pokala, R., Goodkind, A., Brizan, D.G., Rosenberg, A., & Phoha, V. Scan-based Evaluation of Continuous Keystroke Authentication Systems. IT Professional, 15(4), 20-23.
- 2008 Goodkind, A. Tracking the Emergence of Narrative Competence in Story Retelling. Quebec Student Journal of Linguistics, Vol. 3.
- 2007 Passonneau, R. J., Goodkind, A., & Levy, E. T. Annotation of Children's Oral Narrations: Modeling Emergent Narrative Skills for Computational Applications. Florida Artificial Intelligence Research Society (FLAIRS), 253-258.
- 2006 Passonneau, R., McKeown, K., Sigelman, S., & Goodkind, A.. Applying the Pyramid Method in the 2006 Document Understanding Conference. Proceedings of the 2006 Workshop of the Document Understanding Conference (DUC).

Presentations

- 2018 Lee, M.A., Martin, G.E., Goodkind, A., Bicknell, K., Maltman, N., Bush, L., Losh, M. A Multi-Method Approach to Characterizing Pragmatic Language Development in Individuals with FXS. Paper presented at the International Fragile X Conference, Cincinnati, OH, July, 2018
 - Goodkind, A.. Complex Data Visualization: Visualizing language production dynamics via keystroke analysis. Presentation at Inaugural Data Science Research Day, Northwestern University Institute on Complex Systems, 25 June 2018. (Slides)
 - Goodkind, A.. Demo of TypeShift software system for tracking keystroke dynamics at Individual Differences Workshop, Northwestern University, 30 May 2018. (Code)

Lee, M.A., Martin, G.E., **Goodkind, A.**, Bicknell, K., Maltman, N., Bush, L., Losh, M. *A longitudinal, multi-method analysis of pragmatic language in ASD and related developmental disabilities.* Poster presented at the International Society for Autism Research, May, 2018, Rotterdam, Netherlands

Goodkind, A. & Bicknell, K.. Low-level language statistics affect reading times independently of surprisal. Poster presentation at the 31st annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing, UC Davis, Davis, California, 15–17 March 2018.

- 2015 Goldman, N. & **Goodkind**, A.. Worth 1,⊕⊕⊕ Words: The Linguistics of Emoji and Emoji of Linguistics. SQUID X: 10th Annual Conference Showcasing Quirky and Original Ideas in Development. New York, NY April 24, 2015. (Slides)
- 2014 Goodkind, A.. Detecting Multi-word Expressions Through Typing Patterns. 15th Texas Linguistics Society Conference, Austin ,TX, October 24-26, 2014 (Slides)

Goodkind, A.. Detecting Multi-word Expressions in Computer Keyboard Produced Text. CUNY Research Day, New York, NY

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

Northwestern University

- Linguistics 220: Language & Society (Prof. Annette D'Onofrio), 2018
 - Guest lecture on quantitative data analysis
- Cognitive Science 210: Language & the Brain (Profs. Matt Goldrick & Mark Beeman), 2019
- Linguistics 221: Language & Prejudice (Prof. Erin Leddon), 2019

Non-Academic	;
EMPLOYMENT	

PhD Data Science Intern, Vail Systems, Chicago, IL, USA	Summer 2020
Language Engineering Intern, Transcendental Endeavors, NY, NY, USA	Summer 2016
Software Developer in Test Intern, Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA	Summer 2013
Operations Analyst, Goldman Sachs, Multiple Locations, USA	2008 – 2011

DEPARTMENTAL SERVICE

2018–Present
2017 - 2018
2017–Present
2017–Present
2016 - 2017
2

Professional Activities

Diversity & Inclusivity Committee, NAACL 2019, Committee Member DevSci Cluster, Northwestern University, Member Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE), Member Linguistic Society of America (LSA), Member Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), Member Financial Industry Regulatory Authority (FINRA), Member

Languages

Computer—Java, Python, R (ggplot2, plotly, lme4), C++, VBA, C#, LATEX, MATLAB/Octave Human—American Sign Language (ASL), Hebrew, Latin